Finding Aid for the Zen Center of Los Angeles records, 1937-2012 LSC.2299
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zen Center of Los Angeles records
1937-2012
1969-2006
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zen Center of Los Angeles
LSC.2299
64.2 Linear Feet (83 boxes, 5 cartons, 3 shoe boxes, 58 flat boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, 1 phonograph box)
The Zen Center of Los Angeles (ZCLA) was founded in 1967 by Taizan Maezumi. Associated with the Soto Zen sect, it provides Buddhist teaching and training to both lay people and monks. This collection spans 1937-2012 and primarily consists of teaching materials, which are both written materials and audio recordings. The collection also includes book manuscripts, Maezumi Roshi's notebooks and personal files, and ZCLA administrative records.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of this collection are closed until the November 26, 2034 due to donor-imposed restrictions. Box 151 is unavailable for access.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL AND DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Zen Center of Los Angeles, 2012.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9980306063606533
Biographical History
The Zen Center of Los Angeles (ZCLA) was founded in 1967 by Taizan Maezumi Roshi. Associated with the Soto Zen sect, ZCLA provides teaching and training to both lay people and monks. ZCLA provides classes, intensive meditation, Buddhist services, workshops, and opportunities for service. Maezumi Roshi was born in Japan on February 24, 191. His father was Soto priest and he was ordained as a novice monk in the Soto lineage at age eleven. He moved to the United States to serve as a priest at the Zenshuji in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles. Maezumi Roshi also founded the White Plum Asanga and the Yokoji Zen Mountain Center. He died unexpectedly while on a trip to Japan in 1995. As of 2017, the Center is under the direction of Roshi Wendy Egyoku Nakao.
Scope and Content
The collection spans 1937-2012, with the core of the collection consisting of teaching materials, which are in both written form and audio recordings. There are dozens of manuscripts for these presentations, or teishos, and approximately 2000 audio cassettes. There are also many book manuscripts in the form of drafts or galley proofs. These include both original works in English and Japanese and translations from Japanese and Chinese. Some of the translations appear to be unpublished. The collection also includes the personal notebooks of Maezumi Roshi. Mostly in Japanese, they appear to contain the notes he kept while preparing his teishos. There is also more personal material related to Maezumi Roshi, consisting of correspondence and many examples of his calligraphy. Also present are many of the Center's publications, as well as its administrative and financial records.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1. Teaching materials, 1970-2002
Series 2. Book manuscripts, 1937-1992
Series 3. Taizan Maezumi Roshi notebooks, 1973-1989
Series 4. Taizan Maezumi Roshi personal files, 1969-1995
Series 5. Publications and printed material, 1955-2012
Series 6. Administrative files, 1969-2011
Series 7. Financial records, 1974-1994
Series 8. Audiovisual material, 1972-2006
Series 9. Books and periodicals, 2005-2006
Related Materials
Ruth Strout McCandless Collection on Nyogen Senzaki (Collection 2296). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Zen Buddhism -- United States.; Maezumi, Hakuyu Taizan -- Archives.; Zen Center of Los Angeles -- Archives
- Series 1. Teaching materials, 1970-2002
  Scope and Content
  This series contains writings that appear to be intended for instruction activities within the Zen Center or affiliated locations. They include notes, lesson plans, formal lectures, and transcriptions of talks and class sessions. Most of the presentations were written by Maezumi Roshi. Some are as short as two pages long, while the lessons on the Book of Equanimity runs hundreds of pages.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Absolute and Relative, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Acupuncture Needle of Zazen, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - All Sentient Beings Have the Wisdom and Virtue of the Tathagata Buddha, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Answer Is Simple, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appreciating This Life, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aspects of Zen Practice, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Basic Practice, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Basics of Zazen, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Be Aware of What a Wonderful Thing We Are Doing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beginner's Mind, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bendowa, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Birth, Sickness, Old Age, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blue Cliff Record, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bodhi Day, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Body and Mind Sitting Straight, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Book of Equanimity, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16-17, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Closing the Gap Between Self and Self, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Comments on Hsin Hsin Ming, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Content of Zazen, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Differences of Soto-Rinzai, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Discrimination and Self-Nature The Foundation on Which We Can Stand & Live Together, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Diversity, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dogen Zenji - Being-Time, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Empty Inside/Harmony Outside, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Enmei Jukku Kannon Gyo: Prolonging Life Ten Phrase Avalokiteshvara Sutra, 1979-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Maezumi Roshi's notes as well as material compiled after his death.
  - Foot Patrol & Tozan's What Is Most Painful?, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fusatsu - Do Not Tell a Lie, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Harmony & Financial Difficulties, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Heart Sutra, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hokyo Zammai Ka: Jeweled Mirror Samadhi, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - How to Do "Shikan", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Impermanence, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Importance of Faith, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Italy, Culture, and Religion, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jukai seminar, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Just Sit!, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kai #2 - Non-Stealing: Put the Whole World in Heart, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Koan of the Seven Wise Sisters, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Koku - Empty Space, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Handwritten notes in Japanese.
  - Koryu Osaka Roshi - Questions and Answers, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Koryu Osaka Roshi - Teishos, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Koryu Roshi Memorial, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Kyuho's Head & Tail, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Lineage, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Meal Gathas, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Mere Sitting Is Not Enough, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - More Fundamentals of Zazen, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - My Childhood by Hakuun Yasutani Roshi, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - No Color, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Obon, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - On Ceremony, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - On Life and Death, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - On the Endeavor of the Way, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - On Zenshuji Conference: Americanization of Temple Structure, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Oxherding Pictures, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Polishing the Tile, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Practice in His Absence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Practicing Jijuyu Samadhi, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Prajna Paramita, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Qi Gong, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Realizing Our True Nature, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Relative and Absolute, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - A Roadmap for Your Zazen, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sandokai, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Segaki: the Service for Hungry Ghosts, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Self-Fulfilling Samadhi and Dharma, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Shakyamuni Buddha and I Are Practicing Together, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Shikantaza - Susofukan, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Shobogenzo Bendowa, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Shobogenzo Genjo Koan, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Shobogenzo: Makahannya Haramitsu, circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Shosan, 1982-1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Shudo, Ishii - seminars (translated by Albert Welter), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Shudo, Ishii - seminars (translated by David Putney), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sila Paramita, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sixteen Stages of Counting the Breath, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sutras, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Teisho on Service, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Tenzo Kyokun - Appreciating One's Life (Joyful Mind), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Think of Not Thinking, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Three Koans and Seven Sisters, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Three "Pillows" of Zen, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trip to Japan and More, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Venerable Jiun, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - What Is Sesshin?, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Wholeheartedly Sit and Clarify the Great Matter!, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Why Do We Recite Sutras?, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Why Practice?, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Why We Do Service, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The Woodcutter and the Animal Called Satori, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Yakusan's Koan on Zazen, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - You Should Really Verify Yourself, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Zazen of Self-Fulfilled Samadhi, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Untitled writings, 1974-1990 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Teaching materials, 1973-1993 (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
- Series 2. Book manuscripts, 1937-1992
  This series contains manuscripts intended for publication at various levels of completion by people associated with the Zen Center, including Maezumi Roshi, Robert Aitken, John Daido Loori, Taigen Daniel Leighton, and Steven S. Krause.
  Manuscripts are listed alphabetically by author. Chinese authors are identified by the Library of Congress transliteration of their names, even if that differs from the transliteration in the work itself.
  - Aitken, Robert - A Book about Basho's Haiku and Zen (penultmate typescript draft), 1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    This was probably published as A Zen Wave; includes a foreword by W.S. Merwin.
  - Burdick, Owen - Paschal Triptych and an essay: Stravinsky's Requiem Canticles, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dogen - Moon in a Dewdrop (edited by Kazuaki Tanahashi; translated by Reb Anderson, Ed Brown, Arnold Kotler, Dan Leighton, Lew Richmond, David Schneider, Kazuaki Tanashi, Katherine Thanas, Brian Unger, Mel Weitsman, Dan Welch, and Philip Whalen), 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
    Scope and Contents
    Part Three, comprising pages 94-193, is missing.
  - Dogen - The True Eye of the Dharma Treasury in Chinese (typescript by unidentified translator), 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Dogen - The True Eye of the Dharma Treasury in Chinese (typescript by unidentified translator), 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Keizan - The Transmission of Light (typescript of translation by Thomas Cleary), 1981 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Kodera, Takashi James - Dogen's Formative Years in China: Historical Study and Annotated Translation of the Hokyo-Ki, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Lao Tzu - Tao Te Ching (typescript translation by Steven S. Krause), 1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Liangje - The Record of Tung-shan Liang-chieh of Jui-chou (typescript by unidentified translator), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Linji - The Recorded Sayings of Ch'an Master Lin-Chi Hui-Chao of Chen Prefecture; compiled by his humble heir Hui-Jan of San-Sheng, circa 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Loori, John Daido - The Eight Gates of Zen, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Loori, John Daido - The Mountain Record of Collected Zen Talks, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Matthiessen, Peter - Nine Headed Dragon River, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Sahn, Seung - The Whole World Is a Single Flower, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Senzaki, Nyogen - The Gateless Gate, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Yuanwu - Hekigan Roku (typescript of translation by Yamada Koun and Robert Aitken), undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Zhaozhou - The Collected Teachings of Zen Master Chao-Chou (translated by James Green), undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Probably published as The Recorded Sayings of Zen Master Joshu.
  - Zhengjue - The Book of Equanimity, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Zhengjue - The Book of Serenity (typescript of translation by Thomas Cleary), 1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Includes several notes from Cleary.
  - Zhengjue - Cultivating the Empty Field (galley proof of translation by Taigen Daniel Leighton with Yi Wu), 1991 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Zhengjue - Shoyo Roku (typescript translation by Maezumi Roshi and Dana Fraser), undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified - Shobogenzo Genjo Koan: an Analytic Study, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified translation of Buddhist text, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts in Japanese, undated (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
- Series 3. Taizan Maezumi Roshi notebooks, 1973-1989 (Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26)
  This series consists of various notebooks and three-ring binders maintained by Taizan Maezumi Roshi. Each folder typically includes handwritten notes in Japanese and/or English as well as a several annotated texts in Japanese and English.
- Series 4. Taizan Maezumi Roshi personal files, 1969-1995
  This series contains material belonging to Maezumi Roshi but not directly related to his teaching. It consists mostly of personal correspondence and calligraphy. Many of the materials are in Japanese, including all of the calligraphy, journal and correspondence.
  - Biographical material, 1978-1998 (Box 27)
  - Calligraphy, 1977-1983 (Box 27, Box 28, Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1995 (Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 151)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 151 of the correspondence is restricted until November 26, 2034 at the request of the donor.
  - Journal, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Poetry, 1989-1993 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    Contains two volumes of handwritten poetry by "Kyoshin," inspired by and dedicated to Maezumi Roshi.
- Series 5. Publications and printed material, 1955-2012
  This series consists of periodicals published by the Center, ranging from the informal newsletters to the professionally published literary magazine ZCLA Journal. The printed material consists of short pamphlets and brochures, and in a few cases, photocopies of Japanese books.
  - Newsletters, 1976-1985 (Box 34, Box 35)
    Includes the monthly newsletters circulated to members.
  - Sangha Letter, 1985-2000 (Box 36)
  - The Ten Directions, 1980-1994 (Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39)
  - Water Wheel, 2002-2012 (Box 40)
  - ZCLA Journal, 1971-1975 (Box 41)
  - Booklets, pamphlets, and other printed materials, 1955-2004 (Box 42, Folder 1-3)
    Includes: "Essentials and Symbols of the Buddhist Faith"; "Samma Samadhi: Being an Exposition of the Method of Samatha-Vipassana as Discovered & Attained by All Buddhas"; Institute of Asian Cultures material [in French and Japanese]; "Zen Flashes" by Roshi Egyoku Nakao.
  - Booklets, pamphlets, and other printed materials in Japanese and Chinese, undated (Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45)
- Series 6. Administrative files, 1969-2011
  This series contains material about the day-to-day operations of the Center, information about various programs and affiliated organizations, and member information.
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1981-1996 (Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49)
  - Calendars, date books, and address books, 1974-1994 (Box 50, Box 51)
  - Greyston Family Inn, 1987 (Box 52)
  - Guest books, 1978-1995 (Box 52)
  - High Holy Days material, 2001-2005 (Box 53, Box 54)
    Contains material related to Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur services held at ZCLA.
  - Kuroda Institute, 1979-1992 (Box 55)
  - Maezumi Roshi's death, 1995 (Box 56)
    Contains material relating to Maezumi's death; includes his last will and testament, condolence letters, information about memorial services, memorial issue of the journal Mountain Record, Fall 1995.
  - Member records, 1988-1994 (Box 57)
  - Monks' registration papers, 1973- 1990 (Box 58)
  - Procedural manuals, 1983-1997 (Box 59, Box 60)
    Contains documents detailing how various classes and events at the center should be conducted.
  - Publicity material, 1976-1993 (Box 61, Box 62)
  - Staff files, 1977 -1985 (Box 63)
    RESTRICTED MATERIAL. Social security numbers need to be redacted.
  - White Plum Asanga records, 1982-1999 (Box 64, Box 65)
    This file contains material relating to the Zen school established by Maezumi Roshi. It includes correspondence, membership information, schedules and procedures for meetings, other administrative records, and a medal from the City College of New York.
  - Yokoji Zen Mountain Center - plans and photographs, circa 1982-1994 (Box 66, Folder 1-3)
  - Administrative files, 1969-2011 (Box 45, Box 66, Box 67, Box 68, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 72, Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76, Box 77)
- Series 7. Financial records, 1974-1994
  This series includes budget information, financial reports, bank statements, receipts, and donation records
  - Property tax exemption, 1979 (Box 78)
  - Financial records, 1974-1994 (Box 45, Box 79, Box 80, Box 81, Box 82, Box 83, Box 84)
- Series 8. Audiovisual material, 1972-2006
  Most of this material consists of recordings of teishos, seminars, lectures, and other events at the ZCLA.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL AND DIGITAL] MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Audio cassettes, 1972-2002 (Box 85, Box 86, Box 87, Box 88, Box 89, Box 90, Box 91, Box 92, Box 93, Box 94, Box 95, Box 96, Box 97, Box 98, Box 99, Box 100, Box 101, Box 102, Box 103, Box 104, Box 105, Box 106, Box 107, Box 108, Box 109, Box 110, Box 111, Box 112, Box 113, Box 114, Box 115, Box 116, Box 117, Box 118, Box 119, Box 120, Box 121, Box 122, Box 123, Box 124, Box 125, Box 126, Box 127, Box 128, Box 129, Box 130, Box 131, Box 132, Box 133, Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137, Box 138, Box 139, Box 140)
    The audio cassettes are mostly recordings of teishos, seminars, or lectures. They are typically labelled with a title, speaker, and date. There are approximately 2000 of them. Boxes 85-121 mostly contain talks by Maezumi Roshi, and boxes 122-140 mostly contain talks by others.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - CD-Rs, 2003-2004 (Box 141)
    Ten discs of various talks.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Open reel audiotape, 1970-1971 (Box 141)
    Four tapes, content unknown.
  - VHS, U-matic, and open reel videotape, 1978-1999 (Box 141, Box 142, Box 143, Box 144)
    Thirty-four VHS cassettes, one Beta cassette (with a label in Korean), one U-matic tape, and one videotape reel. Most of the tapes appear to be of teishos or special services. A few are television programs or short films with some connection to Zen practice. Two of the tapes appear to be of Maezumi Roshi's funeral.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - ZCLA Talk Archive, 2005-2006 (Box 145)
    Ninety-nine CD-Rs in two three-ring binders with talks by various individuals.
- Series 9. Books and periodicals, 1963-1994 (Box 146, Box 147, Box 148, Box 149, Box 150)
  Most of these are about Zen or other aspects of Buddhism, but there are also reference books and books about art.